Guide to the Humanities Council Records RG.9.5.1
New York University Archives
- Series IV: Projects, 1982-1996; 1 VHS; 82 audiocassettes; 747 kilobytes in 62 computer files; 15.25 Linear Feet in 29 manuscript boxes, 2 half-manuscript boxes, and 11 folders in oversize flat boxes
  - Subseries IV.D: Other Projects, 1986-1996; 4.25 Linear Feet in 8 manuscript boxes, 1 half-manuscript box, and 2 folders in oversize flat boxes; 331.3 kilobytes in 29 computer files; 2 audiocassettes
    In the late 1980s and 1990s, the Humanities Council planned other projects tied to historical milestones or with other institutions. In 1986, Council Director Leslie Berlowitz began working on America in Theory, a volume of essays published by Oxford University Press in 1988. The essays explored how social programs enacted by the federal government were explained, justified, and promoted with a discourse on "American Ideals." This work was not explicitly tied to the U. S. Constitution Bicentennial in 1987, but its themes relate to other discussions, events, and programs the Council was engaged with at the time. In 1991 and 1992, the Council again collaborated with the Museum of the City of New York on an exhibition titled "Democracy's Poet: A Walt Whitman Celebration" tied to the poet's 100th birthday. Between 1991 and 1995, the Council planned lectures and seminars commemorating the 150th anniversary of Henry James's birth in conjunction with similar events planned by Louisiana State University and the Henry James Society. In 1995, the Council hosted a conference titled "The Appropriation of African-American Culture by the Minstrel Show." This conference was part of a larger group of events, "Exploring the Problem of the Color Line," overseen by the Atlanta Center for History. The same year, the Council hosted a conference commemorating 100 years of film, which was, in turn, one of many events planned by New York City institutions to celebrate the centenary.
    Subseries IV.D Other Projects (dated 1986-1996) contains files related to the America in Theory book, the Walt Whitman exhibition at Museum of the City of New York, Henry James Sesquicentennial programming, and two conferences: one on minstrel shows and one celebrating 100 years of film. The America in Theory file includes essay drafts, correspondence with contributors and the publisher, promotional materials, and planning files for a book release party and other events. The Henry James Sesquicentennial file includes correspondence with other institutions planning similar events, a listing of Henry James seminars, and audio recordings of two lectures. The Whitman Centennary exhibition is documented with posters and correspondence between the Council and the Museum of the City of New York. This subseries includes program proposals, National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposals, and event planning files related to both conferences. The minstrel show conference file also includes budgets, invitations, and "pocket materials" created for conference attendees.
    - America in Theory, 1986-1989
      - Notes, 1986-1988 (Box 56, Folder 4)
      - Included Essays, 1986-1988 (Box 56, Folder 5-10, Box 57, Folder 1-8, Box 58, Folder 1-2, Box 18, Folder 8)
      - Drafts, 1986-1989
        - Paper Records, 1986-1988 (Box 58, Folder 5-9, Box 59, Folder 1)
        - Electronic Records, 1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_91
      - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 56, Folder 1-3)
      - Contracts, 1987-1988 (Box 74, Folder 1)
      - Oxford University Press, 1988-1989 (Box 58, Folder 3-4)
      - Events, 1988-1989 (Box 59, Folder 2-3)
      - Promotional materials and press, 1988-1989 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Walt Whitman Centenary, 1991-1992
      - Paper Records, 1991-1992 (Box 54, Folder 24, Box 87, Folder 1-2)
      - Electronic Records, 1991-1992; RG_9-5-1_ER_78
      - Posters, 1991-1992 (Box 88, Folder 6, Box Shared University Archives 154, Folder 3)
    - Henry James Sesquicentennial, 1991-1995
      - Paper Records, 1991-1995 (Box 66, Folder 7)
      - Electronic Records, 1991-1995; RG_9-5-1_ER_97
      - Lecture: Richard Poirier--"Making Connections", October 22, 1992 (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0017)
      - Lecture: Richard Poirier--"The Burdening of Voice", October 15, 1992 (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0020)
      - Seminars, 1995 (Box 66, Folder 13)
    - "The Appropriation of African-American Culture by the Minstrel Show"--Conference at NYU, 1993-1996
      - Proposal to Atlanta Center for History, 1993-1994 (Box 67, Folder 7)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities Proposal, 1994-1996 (Box 67, Folder 5-6)
      - Planning Files, Spring 1994
        - Paper Records, 1994-1996 (Box 67, Folder 8)
        - Electronic Records, 1994; RG_9-5-1_ER_99
      - Budget, 1994 (Box 67, Folder 9)
      - Invitations to Participants, 1994-1995 (Box 67, Folder 10)
      - Pocket Materials, 1995 (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - Celebration of 100 Years of Film, 1993-1996
      - Program Proposals, 1993 (Box 66, Folder 8)
      - Planning Files, 1993-1994 (Box 66, Folder 9-11)
      - NYU Planning Committee, 1993-1994 (Box 66, Folder 12)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities Proposal Drafts, 1993-1994 (Box 67, Folder 3)
      - Luncheon for New York City Institutions, February 15, 1994 (Box 67, Folder 1)
      - Breakfast for New York City Institutions, May 25, 1994 (Box 67, Folder 2)
      - Cinema Turns 100: An Interntional Conference Celebrating the Centennial of Commercial Motion Picture, 1994 (Box 67, Folder 4)
- Series V. Audio Recordings, circa 1976-1996; 2.75 Linear Feet in 7 cassette boxes and 1 record carton; 2 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel; 17 audiocassettes
  Series V: Audio Recordings (dated 1976-1996) contains recordings that could not be arranged into series based on their labels alone.
  This series is arranged chronologically. Undated materials are listed alphabetically following the chronological listing.
  - Myong, September 29, 1980 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0221)
  - Ruddick, Kamm, and Wilcox, May 5, 1983 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0211)
  - Tisch Auditorium, June 19, 1991 (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0259)
  - Beret, Maxwell, undated (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0164)
  - Humanities Council, undated (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0164)
  - John Kuntz, Cy Knoblouch, undated (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0182)
  - Syndsson and Spector, undated (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0199)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 91, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0268)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0217)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 96, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0220)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 95, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0190)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 90, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0162)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0106)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 93, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0107)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0005)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0021)
  - Unlabeled Audiocassette, undated (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0022)
  - Unlabeled Audio Reel, undated (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 9-5-1.0069)
  - Unlabeled Audio Reel, undated (Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 9-5-1.0073)